Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 9: Preconceptional Counseling.
Counseling Session Medical History Genetic Diseases Reproductive History Parental Age Social History Screening Tests References The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) defines preconceptional health to encompass the overall health of nonpregnant women during their reproductive years .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019b) and the Society for Maternal–Fetal Medicine (2014, 2021) attest to the importance of preconceptional care and promote the following objectives to advance it: 1. Improve knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors of men and women related to preconceptional health 2.
Assure that all childbearing-aged women receive preconceptional care services—including evidence-based risk screening, health promotion, and interventions—that will enable them to enter pregnancy in optimal health 3.
Implement interconceptional interventions to prevent or minimize recurrent adverse outcomes 4.
Reduce the racial and socioeconomical disparities in adverse pregnancy outcomes Table 9-1.
lists the prevalence of many conditions often amenable to preconceptional intervention .
These are frequently encountered by generalist obstetrician–gynecologists, who can help optimize health entering pregnancy .
For example, by the time most women realize they are pregnant—usually 1 to 2 weeks after the first missed period—the embryo has already begun to form.
Thus, many preventive steps —such as folic acid to avoid neural-tube defects—will be ineffective if initiated at this time.
Moreover, 45 percent of all pregnancies in the United States are unplanned, and often these are at greatest risk .
Last, a disproportionate number of indigent women receive less preconceptional care compared with their more affluent counterparts .
TABLE 9-1.
Preconceptional Health Indicators—United States, 2013–2015 Few randomized trials evaluate preconceptional care efficacy, in part because withholding such counseling would be unethical.
Also, pregnancy outcomes are dependent on the interaction of various maternal, fetal, and environmental factors.
Thus, ascribing a salutary outcome to a specific intervention is difficult (Temel, 2014; Tieu, 2017).
However, prospective observational and case-control studies have demonstrated the successes of preconceptional counseling .
Therefore, routine pregnancy intention screening should be done .
Counseling Session.
Obstetricians–gynecologists, internists, family practitioners, and pediatricians have the best opportunity to provide preventive counseling during periodic health maintenance examinations.
The occasion of a negative pregnancy test is also an excellent time for education .
Jack and colleagues (1995) administered a comprehensive preconceptional risk survey to 136 such women, and almost 95 percent reported at least one problem that could affect a future pregnancy .
Providers should be knowledgeable regarding relevant medical diseases, prior surgery, reproductive disorders, or genetic conditions and be able to interpret data and recommendations provided by other specialists .
Women presenting specifically for preconceptional evaluation are advised that information collection may be time consuming, depending on the number and complexity of factors.
The intake evaluation includes a thorough review of the medical, obstetrical, social, and family histories.
Useful information is more likely to be obtained by asking specific questions regarding each of these histories and the health of each family member than by asking general, open-ended questions.
Some important information can be obtained by questionnaires that address these topics.
Answers are reviewed with the couple to ensure appropriate follow-up, including obtaining relevant medical records.
# The Fourth Trimester.
Another optimal time to begin preconceptional counseling is during the “fourth trimester.
This was emphasized by the Presidential Task Force on Redefining the Postpartum Visit .
Designed to optimize postpartum care and provide
contraceptive counseling, it also sets the stage for any subsequent pregnancy and for the woman’s long-term health.
To assist the provider, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019b) has joined the Society of Maternal–Fetal Medicine to provide an Obstetric Care Consensus guide that emphasizes the interpregnancy period.
Medical History.
With specific medical conditions, general points include the pregnancy’s effect on the condition and the disorder’s influence on the fetus and pregnancy course.
Some chronic conditions that may worsen pregnancy outcomes include treated or active cancer, prior peripartum cardiomyopathy, antiphospholipid antibodies, systemic lupus erythematosus, and congenital heart disease (Amant, 2015; Cunningham, 2019; Davis, 2021; Foeller, 2018; Gibbins, 2018; Hopkins, 2018).
Importantly, psychological health also is considered (Barker, 2020; Lassi, 2014).
Detailed preconceptional information regarding a few exemplary conditions is found in the next sections and in the other topic-specific chapters of this text.
# Diabetes Mellitus.
Because maternal and fetal pathology associated with hyperglycemia is well known, diabetes is the prototype of a condition for which preconceptional counseling is beneficial.
Diabetes-associated risks to both mother and fetus are discussed in detail in Chapter 60 (p. 1068).
If a patient maintains glucose levels close to normal, many of these complications can be avoided before conception.
Another important aspect of counseling pertains to the frequent use of teratogenic angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors in this population .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018f) has concluded that preconceptional counseling for women with pregestational diabetes is beneficial and cost-effective and should be encouraged.
The American Diabetes Association (2004) has promulgated consensus recommendations for preconceptional care for women with diabetes.
These guidelines advise an inventory of disease duration and related complications and clinical and laboratory examination for end-organ damage.
Perhaps most essential, they encourage a preconceptional hemoglobin A1c level goal below 7 percent.
In addition to assessing diabetic control, hemoglobin A1c measurement can also forecast the risks for gestational diabetes and for major anomalies (Hinkle, 2018; Martin, 2020).
Figure 9-1.
Relationship between first-trimester glycosylated hemoglobin values and risk for major congenital malformations in 320 women with insulin-dependent diabetes.
Although no randomized trials attest to the success of preconceptional counseling in women with diabetes, cohort studies do demonstrate its effectiveness .
In a prospective study of 5075 affected women, preconceptional counseling improved hemoglobin A1c levels, folic acid compliance, and “optimal” pregnancy preparation .
Diabetic women who undergo preconceptional counseling also have improved glycemic control before pregnancy and in the first trimester and experience lower rates of adverse outcomes—defined as a perinatal death or major congenital anomaly .
Despite such benefits, in one study of approximately 300 diabetic women in a managed-care plan, only approximately half received preconceptional counseling .
# Epilepsy.
Compared with unaffected women, those with a seizure disorder carry an augmented risk of neonates with structural anomalies.
Some early reports indicated that epilepsy conferred an elevated a priori risk for congenital malformations that was independent of anticonvulsant treatment effects.
More recent studies have largely failed to confirm this, but it is difficult to refute entirely because women who are controlled without medication generally have less severe disease (Cassina, 2013; Vajda, 2015).
Polytherapy is associated with a higher malformation risk compared with monotherapy .
Last, in women using antiseizure medications, the risks for miscarriage and stillbirth in do not appear elevated (Aghajanian, 2015; Bech, 2014).
Ideally, medications are adjusted preconceptionally to
minimize seizure frequency.
From one national registry, the seizure risk during pregnancy was 50 to 70 percent lower in women without a seizure in the year preceding pregnancy compared with a group experiencing seizures in this preceding year .
No further advantages accrued if the seizure-free period exceeded a year.
Treatment goals attempt to control seizure frequency with monotherapy and with medications considered less teratogenic (Aguglia, 2009; Tomson, 2009).
Discussed in Chapter 63 (p. 1129) and shown in Table 9-2, some onedrug regimens are more teratogenic than others.
In particular, valproic acid is avoided if possible, as it has consistently been associated with a greater risk for major congenital malformations than other antiepileptic drugs (Jentink, 2010; Vajda, 2015).
Information concerning the teratogenicity of newer antiepileptics is limited .
Table 9-2.
First-Trimester Antiepileptic Monotherapy and the Associated Major Malformation Risk The American Academy of Neurology recommends consideration of antiseizure medication discontinuation before pregnancy in suitable candidates .
These include women who satisfy the following criteria: (1) have been seizure-free for 2 to 5 years, (2) display a single seizure type, (3) have a normal neurological examination and normal intelligence, and (4) show electroencephalogram results that have normalized with treatment.
Women with seizures should be advised to take a daily 4-mg oral folic acid supplement.
Even so, the value of folate to reduce fetal malformation rates in pregnant women taking anticonvulsant therapy is not entirely clear.
In one case-control study, the congenital abnormality risk was reduced by maternal folate supplementation in fetuses exposed to carbamazepine, phenobarbital, phenytoin, and primidone (Kjær, 2008).
Conversely, Morrow and coworkers (2009) compared fetal outcomes of women who received preconceptional folic acid with those who did not receive it until later in pregnancy or not at all.
In this study, a paradoxical increase in the number of major congenital malformations was observed in the group who received preconceptional folate.
These investigators concluded that folate metabolism may be only a part of the mechanism by which malformations are induced in women taking these medications.
# Immunizations.
Preconceptional counseling includes assessment of immunity against common pathogens.
Also, depending on health status, travel plans, and time of year, other immunizations may be indicated as discussed in Chapter 10 (p. 189).
Several immunization resources are listed in Table 9-3.
Vaccines that contain toxoids such as tetanus are suitable before or during gestation.
Also, those containing killed bacteria or viruses—such as influenza, pneumococcus, hepatitis B, meningococcus, and rabies vaccines—are not associated with adverse fetal outcomes and are not contraindicated preconceptionally or during pregnancy.
Conversely, live-virus vaccines are not recommended during pregnancy.
Examples are vaccines against varicella-zoster, measles, mumps, rubella, polio, chickenpox, and yellow fever.
Moreover, 1 month or longer should ideally pass between vaccination and conception attempts.
That said, inadvertent administration of measles, mumps, rubella (MMR) or varicella vaccines during pregnancy should not generally be considered indications for pregnancy termination.
Most reports indicate that the fetal risk is only theoretical.
Immunization to smallpox, anthrax, and other bioterrorism diseases is discussed if clinically appropriate .
Table 9-3.
Immunization Resources With some infections, vaccines are unavailable.
One recent example is the Zika virus .
For this virus, during the 2016 epidemic, the CDC issued travel advisories for pregnant women (Petersen, 2016; SchulerFaccini, 2016).
Genetic Diseases.
The CDC (2016) estimates that 3 percent of neonates born each year in the United States will have at least one birth defect.
Importantly, such defects are the leading cause of infant mortality and account for 20 percent of deaths.
Ethics preclude
randomized trials of preconceptional counseling for genetic risk .
Instead, the benefits of preconceptional counseling usually are measured by comparing the incidence of new cases before and after initiation of such a program.
Specific congenital conditions that clearly benefit from patient education include neural-tube defects, phenylketonuria, thalassemias, and other genetic diseases more common in individuals of Eastern European Jewish descent .
Other missed opportunities for genetic consultation were found for women with a personal or family history of birth defects, intellectual disability or autism, and a prior positive genetic carrier screening test .
# Family History.
Pedigree construction using the symbols shown in Figure 9-2 is the most thorough method for obtaining a family history as a part of genetic screening.
The health and reproductive status of each “blood relative” are individually reviewed for medical illnesses, mental retardation, birth defects, infertility, and pregnancy loss.
Certain racial, ethnic, or religious backgrounds may indicate elevated risk for specific recessive disorders.
Figure 9-2.
Symbols used for pedigree construction.
Although most women can provide information regarding their history, their understanding may be limited.
Pregnant women may fail to communicate a birth defect in the family or may report it incorrectly.
Thus, any disclosed defect or genetic disease is ideally confirmed by reviewing pertinent medical records or by contacting affected relatives for additional information.
# Neural-Tube Defects.
The incidence of neural-tube defects (NTDs) is 0.9 per 1000 live births, and they are second only to cardiac anomalies as the most frequent structural fetal malformation.
Some of these malformations are associated with specific mutations.
One example is the 677C → T substitution in the gene that encodes methylene tetrahydrofolate reductase.
For this and similar gene defects, one seminal trial showed that preconceptional folic acid therapy significantly reduced the risk for a recurrent NTD by 72 percent .
More importantly, because more than 90 percent of neonates with NTDs are born to women at low risk, Czeizel and Dudas (1992) showed that universal supplementation reduced the a priori risk of a first NTD.
Because of these findings, all women who may become pregnant are recommended to take daily 400 to 800 μg of folic acid orally before conception and through the first trimester (U.S. Preventive Services Task Force, 2019).
Folate fortification of cereal grains has been mandatory in the United States since 1998, and this practice has lowered neural-tube defect rates .
Despite the demonstrated benefits of folate supplementation, only half of women take folic acid supplementation periconceptionally (de Jong-van den Berg, 2005; Goldberg, 2006).
# Phenylketonuria.
More than 600 mutations have been identified in the phenylalanine hydroxylase gene.
The inherited defect in phenylalanine metabolism exemplifies diseases in which the fetus may not be at risk to inherit the disorder but may be damaged by maternal disease.
Specifically, mothers with phenylketonuria (PKU) who eat an unrestricted diet have abnormally high blood phenylalanine levels.
This amino acid readily crosses the placenta and can damage developing fetal organs, especially neural and cardiac tissues.
With appropriate preconceptional counseling and adherence to a phenylalanine-restricted diet before pregnancy, the incidence of fetal malformations is dramatically reduced (Camp, 2014; Vockley, 2014).
Therefore, the phenylalanine concentration is ideally brought into normal range 3 months before conception and then maintained there throughout pregnancy .
The target phenylalanine blood concentration is 120 to 360 µmol/L .
# Thalassemias.
These disorders of globin-chain synthesis are the most common single-gene disorders worldwide (Forget, 2013; Vichinsky, 2013).
As many as 200 million people carry a gene for one of these hemoglobinopathies, and hundreds of mutations are known to cause thalassemia syndromes .
In endemic
areas such as Mediterranean and Southeast Asian countries, counseling and other prevention strategies have reduced the incidence of new cases by up to 80 percent .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018a) recommends that individuals of high-risk ancestry be offered carrier screening to allow them informed decision-making regarding reproduction and prenatal diagnosis.
One method of early prenatal diagnosis for some thalassemia syndromes is preimplantation genetic testing (PGT), which is coupled with assisted reproductive technology .
# Individuals of Eastern European Jewish Descent.
Most individuals of Jewish ancestry in North America are descended from Ashkenazi Jewish communities and are at greater risk for having offspring with one of several autosomal recessive disorders.
These include Tay-Sachs disease, Gaucher disease, cystic fibrosis, Canavan disease, familial dysautonomia, mucolipidosis IV, Niemann-Pick disease type A, Fanconi anemia group C, and Bloom syndrome.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017a; 2019a) recommends preconceptional counseling and screening for these disorders in this population.
Carrier frequency and features of these conditions are discussed in greater detail in Chapter 17 (p. 343).
Reproductive History.
During preconceptional screening, information is sought regarding infertility; abnormal pregnancy outcomes that may include miscarriage, ectopic pregnancy, molar pregnancy, and recurrent pregnancy loss; and obstetrical complications such as cesarean delivery, preeclampsia, placental abruption, and preterm delivery .
As discussed in Chapter 35 (p. 626), details involving a prior stillbirth are especially important.
For example, Korteweg and associates (2008) identified chromosomal abnormalities in 13 percent of stillborns who underwent karyotyping.
And, Reddy and colleagues (2012) confirmed that chromosomal microarray analysis (CMA) yields better detection of genetic abnormalities than does standard karyotyping.
This primarily stems from CMA’s ability to assess nonviable tissue .
Identification of a genetic abnormality in a stillborn can help to determine recurrence risk.
Parental Age.
# Maternal Age.
Women at both ends of the reproductive-age spectrum have unique outcomes to consider.
First, according to the CDC, 3.4 percent of births in the United States in 2010 were in women aged 15 to 19 years .
An international study reported a rate of 11.9 percent for this age group globally .
These adolescents are at higher risk for anemia, preterm delivery, and preeclampsia compared with women aged 20 to 35 years .
The incidence of sexually transmitted diseases—common in adolescents—is even higher during pregnancy .
Unfortunately, because most of their pregnancies are unplanned, adolescents rarely seek preconceptional counseling.
Conceptions after age 35 currently constitute approximately 15 percent of pregnancies in the United States .
By contrast, these women are more likely to request preconceptional counseling.
Motivations may stem from a desire to optimize outcomes at their age or with infertility treatment or both.
Some studies—including data from Parkland Hospital presented in Figure 9-3.
indicate that risks for obstetrical complications and for perinatal morbidity and mortality rise after age 35 (Waldenström, 2015).
The older woman who has a chronic illness or who is in poor physical condition usually has readily apparent risks.
For the physically fit woman without medical problems, however, the risks are lower.
Figure 9-3.
Incidence of selected pregnancy complications in relation to maternal age among 295,667 women delivered at Parkland Hospital.
Overall, the maternal mortality rate is higher in women aged 35 and older .
Creanga and coworkers (2017) analyzed pregnancy-related deaths in the United States for 2011 through 2013.
Although women older than 35 years contributed less than 15 percent of all live births, they constituted 31 percent of maternal deaths.
For the fetus, maternal age-related risks primarily originate from (1)
indicated preterm delivery for maternal complications such as hypertension and diabetes, (2) spontaneous preterm birth, (3) fetal-growth disorders related to chronic maternal disease or multifetal gestation, (4) fetal aneuploidy, and (5) pregnancies resulting from assisted reproductive technology.
Assisted Reproductive Technologies Recall that older women have subfertility problems.
And, although the incidence of dizygotic twinning rises with maternal age, the more important cause of multifetal gestation in older women follows the use of assisted reproductive technology (ART) and ovulation induction.
Indeed, according to the CDC, 30 to 40 percent of all multifetal gestations in the United States in 2012 were conceived with the use of ART .
Morbidity and mortality with multifetal pregnancies stem from preterm delivery and placentation complications, such as placenta previa and abruption .
With ART, transmission of infectious agents is a risk.
For women without human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection who plan conception with their HIV-affected partners, the CDC has published prevention strategies .
Also, Zika virus infection acquisition through in vitro fertilization (IVF) has been described .
Last, some data links ART to higher major congenital malformation rates.
In a registry of 308,974 births, 8.3 percent of neonates conceived by ART had major birth defects, and intracytoplasmic injection was also associated with an elevated risk for malformations .
# Paternal Age.
Advanced paternal age has doubled in the United States over the past generation.
It is associated with a higher risk of preterm birth and new autosomal-dominant mutations .
One example is the possible link between increasing paternal age and complex neuropsychiatric conditions .
Parental history and experiences can also exert effects on progeny through epigenomic information not contained in the DNA sequence.
Variations in sperm and oocyte cytosine methylation and noncoding RNAs are examples (Cedars, 2015; Lane, 2014).
Social History.
# Recreational Drugs and Smoking.
Fetal risks associated with alcohol, marijuana, cocaine, amphetamines, and heroin are discussed in Chapters 8 (p. 148) and 64 (p. 1150).
The first step in preventing drug-related fetal risk is an honest assessment of use by the patient .
Toward this end, questioning should be nonjudgmental.
Several validated tools screen for at-risk drinking.
One is the wellstudied TACE questions .
These four questions investigate having a tolerance to alcohol, being annoyed by comments about their drinking, attempting to cut down, and drinking early in the morning—the eye opener.
Of more than 1000 postpartum patients in one Canadian study, a high percentage reported alcohol use concurrent with conception attempts .
Specifically, nearly half of those planning for pregnancy consumed a mean of 2.2 drinks daily during early gestation and before they recognized their pregnancy.
This frequency and pattern clearly underscore the opportunity for preconceptional counseling.
In 2014 to 2015, 17 percent of reproductive-age women in the United States smoked cigarettes according to the CDC .
Smoking in pregnancy is consistently associated with numerous adverse perinatal outcomes .
These risks are largely mitigated by cessation before pregnancy, highlighting the importance of screening for tobacco use prior to and during pregnancy .
# Environmental Exposures.
Only a few environmental agents have been shown to cause adverse pregnancy outcomes (McCue, 2019; Windham, 2008).
For example, contact with some chemicals may impart significant maternal and fetal risks.
Discussed in Chapter 8 (p. 153), excess exposure to methyl mercury or lead is associated with neurodevelopmental disorders.
For lead, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018b) endorses guidelines that recommend blood lead testing only if a lead-exposure risk factor is identified.
If the levels are >5 µg/dL, counseling is completed, and the lead source is sought and removed.
Blood lead levels >45 µg/dL are consistent with lead
poisoning, and women in this group may be candidates for chelation therapy .
In contrast, everyday exposures to electromagnetic fields are not linked to adverse fetal outcomes .
Examples include energy emanated by high-voltage power lines, electric blankets, microwave ovens, and cellular phones.
# Diet.
Pica is the craving for and consuming of ice, laundry starch, clay, dirt, or other nonfood items.
It should be discouraged due to its inherent replacement of healthful food with nutritionally empty products .
In some cases, it may represent an unusual physiological response to iron deficiency .
Many vegetarian diets are protein deficient but can be corrected by increasing egg and cheese consumption.
Anorexia and bulimia raise maternal risks of nutritional deficiencies, electrolyte disturbances, cardiac arrhythmias, and gastrointestinal pathology .
Discussed in Chapter 64 (p. 1149), pregnancy-related complications with these eating disorders include greater risks of low birthweight, smaller head circumference, microcephaly, and small-for-gestational-age newborns.
Obesity is linked with several maternal complications.
Discussed in Chapter 51 (p. 905), these include hypertension, preeclampsia, gestational diabetes, labor abnormalities, cesarean delivery, and operative complications .
Obesity also appears to be associated with a range of structural fetal anomalies .
# Exercise.
Conditioned pregnant women usually can continue to exercise throughout gestation .
Discussed in Chapter 10, covering prenatal care (p. 187), no data suggest that exercise is harmful during pregnancy.
However, as pregnancy progresses, balance problems and joint relaxation may predispose to orthopedic injury.
During exercise, gravidas should avoid exhaustion, overheating, dehydration, and prolonged supine position.
# Intimate-Partner Violence.
Pregnancy can exacerbate interpersonal problems and is a time of elevated risk from an abusive partner.
According to the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2012), approximately 324,000 pregnant women are abused each year.
Intimate-partner violence (IPV) is associated with greater risk for several pregnancy-related complications that include hypertension, vaginal bleeding, hyperemesis, preterm delivery, and lowbirthweight neonates .
Because IPV can escalate during pregnancy, even to the point of homicide, the preconceptional period provides an ideal time for screening and intervention .
In support, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019c) provides recommendations and resources for screening both pregnant and nonpregnant women for IPV.
# Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer.
Individuals Preconceptional care has traditionally been based on the assumption of heterosexuality and has often excluded lesbian women .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018c) endorses quality health care for all women regardless of sexual orientation.
Indeed, in a study by Carpinello and colleagues (2016), three fourths of lesbian couples planned for one partner to conceive.
Paradoxically, adolescent bisexual and lesbian women are at greater risk for undesired pregnancies (Charlton, 2018; Hodson, 2017).
Of special risks in this group, lesbian and bisexual women have higher incidences of obesity, tobacco and alcohol use, depression, diabetes, and low parity compared with heterosexual women (Mravcak, 2006; O’Hanlan, 2007).
In some of these groups, knowledge of surrogacy laws is imperative .
Screening Tests.
Highlighted in Table 9-4, women with certain chronic medical diseases ideally would be evaluated before conception.
With several of these, optimizing maternal condition will improve pregnancy outcomes.
Table 9-4.
Selected Preconceptional Counseling Topics